[SPEAKER_00]: There was one, Majjhima Nikaya 128, Bhakyalesa, and he basically, he's talking to these bhikkhus, and he asks them if they've attained any superhuman state in meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they talk about perception of light, and vision of forms arising, and then
[SPEAKER_00]: Going away, and they don't know why.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he talks about doubt, excitement, desire for more of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hindrances, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just wanted some clarification on the perception of light, the forms aspect of it, like, what does that refer to exactly?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, see, the Buddha gave the answer there,
[SPEAKER_02]: By, eh... telling them they need to overcome the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, if you want to understand it, you have to be free from hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, whatever answer is given, you'll be doubtful about it, but then you won't see that, because you think, well, that's what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, eh... just... if you need to wrap your head around it,
[SPEAKER_02]: But don't take it as an answer-answer, or that's what perception of light is, because it isn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is when you see it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you need to wrap your head around it, but not confuse it for an answer, well, even take it on a most mundane level, a phenomenon of light, phenomenon of presence, phenomenon of non-dark.
[SPEAKER_02]: Brightness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Brightness, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any epithet you can give it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that is real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: Usually, when minds are just, on average, drenched with sensuality and so on, all these things are kind of abstract or mystical.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if the mind dries up, then you could actually just determine to be percipient of bright.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing specifically.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same sense, you could determine to be percipient of infinite space.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, yeah, signless development of a mind turned away from picking on any nimitta, which is thus animitta.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, like, yeah, you know, I had before people ask, oh yeah, you want to understand the first jhāna, and then this is in the second jhāna, and this is the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Four jhāna, I don't quite get this aspect.
[SPEAKER_02]: Could you clarify?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, are you saying you have developed the three jhānas?
[SPEAKER_02]: In which case, you wouldn't be asking about the fourth, because it's the same principle, but it's like, no, it's just this information that I wrap my head around, that it's satisfying for me, because I think now that's what jhānas are and that's okay, but they're not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if the Buddha himself describes to the utmost detail what the perception of light or what the third jhāna is, it isn't for as long as you don't see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the danger is obviously not like, oh, so I shouldn't learn or get information, but I should be very careful to not conflate it with the actual development of that thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's exactly, see, for as long as they're doubtful, they couldn't quite understand it, why, how, and all the other kind of more particular permutations in regard to the phenomenon of light.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if they're free from that, if the mind has been freed from hindrances,
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's where you put the emphasis on, not on clarifying this, which I would like to know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you get to know it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why would you think it's relevant, the perception of light?
[SPEAKER_02]: What would you expect from it, in terms of meditation?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or was it just, oh, I can't wrap my head around it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I actually wrote notes down about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, okay, what does this perception of light refer to?
[SPEAKER_00]: I looked at the Pali and it's like understanding that brings this sort of light, the phenomena of light, this brightness, understanding, clarity in things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how I took it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it was still, I think, the translation of
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, like, you see something in meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see this light, these visible forms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, well, mind you, most of the, most of the, well, instructions that I heard, it's on the level of, like, even nimittas are regarded that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you close your eyes and you see something.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's these mystical things that you kind of, kind of just see in your meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And nimittas are significance and signs and features that you, you do see on a day-to-day level, from the most coarse to the most... it's the same thing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, it's most certainly not the perception of light, or some source, or something, the way people would...
[SPEAKER_00]: It can just be read so, like, in that form, in that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on the level, like, the reason why the Buddha did talk about that, or other kind of seemingly mystical-sounding properties, it's because when you practice that mind turning away,
[SPEAKER_02]: From things in jhāna, in the first jhāna, in the second jhāna, in the third jhāna, these things are the properties, the aspects that one could then kind of use and also to discern that turning away of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, for example,
[SPEAKER_02]: Turning away of citta, when it turns away from vittaka-vicāra in the first jhāna, as in when it surmounts it, when it is not hindered by movements of vittaka-vicāra, is light, is signless, is... you could describe it even in some idiosyncratic ways if you want, but the Buddha being the Buddha, the idiosyncratic ways were the most accurate ways.
[SPEAKER_02]: So now, say, you're not in the first jhāna, distractions got in the way, or you haven't quite fully understood and so on, but you now can use those properties that you have experienced on account of mind, samādhi, vittāka-vicāra, to restart the practice, to re-establish the mind in the same way.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, establish upon that perception of light.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't work for anyone or everyone, because not everyone would experience it the same way.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there are certain universal characteristics of mind turning away from the domain that it just surmounted.
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, from this point of view, you could see that it's nothing mystical about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's... it's... And you could, even as I said, you could take even some
[SPEAKER_02]: mundane experience of peace or a calm mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you were to really look for the universal description that would kind of always encompass that experience, you would find probably relatively similar terms.
[SPEAKER_02]: That then, if you are skilled in training your mind, would be enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: To re-establish the direction of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, and that's the whole, like, satipaṭṭhāna and ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me, he, like, knowing the mind, he experience, I shall experience the mind like this, I shall experience like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I will be liberating the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Liberating the mind he breathes in, liberating the mind he breathes out.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you start already discerning a relationship with that mind and how to communicate to it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, I will make my...
[SPEAKER_02]: Breathing in, I'll make this mind light.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll make this mind weightless.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll make this mind immeasurable.
[SPEAKER_02]: All the properties you would find.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll make this mind completely turn away from any slightest signs and features.
[SPEAKER_02]: I will protect, I will cultivate that animitta meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: But even like in the suttas, like what we recently came across those verses that we mentioned in one of the previous talks about that
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, it's usually commonly translated like, oh, I meditated on the signlessness or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't actually say that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just says, ah, nimitta, bhavemi, or?
[SPEAKER_01]: Bhavemi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I was cultivating signlessness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, sure, yeah, cultivation means meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, does it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Does cultivation mean what you take meditation to mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: It can, if we qualify it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when you say meditation, we all know what that means.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means sitting cross-legged, watching tip of my nose, or something of that kind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Technique.
[SPEAKER_02]: Technique of silenceness, kamatthana that Ajahn gave me.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, no, she turned her mind away from signs and features that would be otherwise inducing of lust, aversion, avidya, and she protected that.
[SPEAKER_02]: She cultivated that until the mind was fully released from going back to things that are now understood as unownable, as perilous, dangerous, not worth the passion, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yes, she meditated on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But not in that in that common sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you just carelessly use this, well, meditate my meditation and so on, it becomes okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's some sort of these nimittas and these lights and these properties that would come on account of understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding this passion, understanding how to turn your mind away from things that are unsuitable, will become this kind of extension of this mystical kind of expectations.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I had this light.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't quite know what it means.
[SPEAKER_02]: It bears no relevance to my ability to suffer, but it was super special.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, must have been jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's a kind of very different picture that you would get reading the suttas, as to, you know, what jhānas would result in, and lead to, and turning away from sensuality, and being unable to be hindered by any of the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is already certain... like, when it comes to consciousness, there is already a certain, like, just radiance to being aware.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't matter what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Presence of something.
[SPEAKER_02]: To that extent, it's lit up.
[SPEAKER_02]: To that extent, it's bright.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's some of the descriptions of consciousness, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it is radiant or bright and...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, on its own.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, people tend to mystify that term.
[SPEAKER_02]: Our consciousness is always pure and bright and eternal and ever... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: It literally means property of that aggregate is such to be bright and luminous all around and not necessarily bound by any subject of perception of ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, as he said many times before, in other suttas, like the upādāna, the assumption, the craving, is not part of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not any of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not in them.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, it's not to be found anywhere else, except where the five aggregates are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Also, it's neither here nor there, so to speak, but it's with them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Says, what is... why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is it like that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, desire and lust, in regards to the five aggregates, upādāna is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: But five aggregates, as I said in, you know, my old essays, they... they're completely unaware of you, unaware of your ownership, unaware of everything you're going through, unaware of each other.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just five heaps.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why they're called khandhas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Khandha just means heaps of stuff, separate from one another.
[SPEAKER_02]: And property of the heap of consciousness is that brightness, lightness, luminosity, whatever else, on its own.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, sure, as we just discussed this, I can mystify that, because I wrap my head around the idea, but one thing is to think it, another thing is to actually see it for yourself, so... And as that... what you... your original question about that, oh, the monks couldn't quite get this perception of light, oh, because they were not free from doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were still accessing it through the abstract notions of it, and thus becoming liable to doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: They haven't developed mind sufficiently.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the one who does develop the mind sufficiently, you just find that consciousness, luminous all around, that is equally impermanent, like the form, like the feeling, like the perception, like saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's nothing special to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But yes, if your mind has been trained and developed and withdrawn from the senses, you can use the property of that light, luminosity, to remove any traces.
[SPEAKER_02]: of ownership and obstruction, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you haven't developed your mind, but like the idea of luminous, unpolluted, and then just take it in a mystical direction, then you feel exempted from everything else, because you explained your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, see, there's always light.
[SPEAKER_02]: Consciousness is eternal, it's pure, it cannot be polluted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, for somebody who is now an arahant, but do you start from that position?
[SPEAKER_02]: If so, the Buddha would have just said, listen monks, the aggregates cannot be polluted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Go home now.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're done here.
[SPEAKER_02]: The whole gradual training, withdrawal, taming, enduring, that khanthi, the whole thing,
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, sure, when you see the luminosity of consciousness, or that, as he described in that casino suit, he says, yeah, it's the most refined of all casinos.
[SPEAKER_02]: But even that, the target understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: The gratification, the danger, the escape in regard to the totality of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even such a pure, refined thing?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even that is not worth holding, adhering, delighting in, finding the safety in.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what people who kind of, you know, have some sort of underlying, either Advaita, non-duality view, cannot understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: In a sense that they cannot understand that that's the difference that the Buddha was teaching.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that he was teaching something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Take whatever concept, idea, sense of release you have found, and you choose, basically, deep down, to regard it as safe, as friendly, as my shelter, as my help, as my reference point.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the whole point is you could equally choose to not regard it so.
[SPEAKER_02]: But people don't choose that, because that's too unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, people always say, oh, well, like, you know, it's love and light, it's your true being, it's your intrinsic self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, see, you know, when you experience these things, they, you know, they just happen like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, oh, yeah, that is true.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when you experience suffering and pain, that's also your intrinsic being.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, why would you experience it in the first place?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on the same level.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't pick and choose.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_02]: If the life, human life, were only suffering, people would not be enamored with form and sensuality and everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it were only pleasure, well, people would not seek the way out.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you realize, no, I'm liable to both.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's not a good deal for somebody who understands the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even the most refined
[SPEAKER_02]: Concept, idea, sense of safety, experience, meditation, release.
[SPEAKER_02]: You could...
[SPEAKER_02]: If you understood the value of the Buddha's teaching, you could see, oh, even that is not worth taking his mind for me, I am, my safety, my shelter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even that has to be subjected to the same anicca that these coarse things are.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's when the mind turns away and experience dispassion and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's now on the level of much deeper view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you can keep saying that to yourself as a mantra, or this is all anicca, it's all anicca.
[SPEAKER_02]: Deep down, is your mind very much sort of gripped with the joy towards the non-dual experience of the universe you had?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is your mind truly able to, oh, this is dangerous, and feel that peril of even that?
[SPEAKER_02]: And, I mean, he was teaching that in many different regards, but he even said even for jhāna,
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, when everything is factually wholesome in it, the experience, there are no underlying tendencies there, no craving, no hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: And says, and then I tell monks, now monk, regard that as a dot, as a peril, as debt, as unsuitable, as harmful, so the mind will turn away from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you will know it's fully liberated.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing, absolutely nothing is worth clinging to, welcoming, delighting in.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that is very frightening for somebody whose mind is not being developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly when people who were not quite prepared already, went to the Buddha, insisted on certain questions, he answered them, explained what nibbāna is, and they just fell on the ground, pulling their hair with that description, in complete basically anxiety, saying, well, that will kill me, that will destroy me, there will be no me after that.
[SPEAKER_02]: No eternal safety coming from this.
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, it is eternal safety, so to speak, if you truly give up any need for safety.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you will give up any need for safety if you give up the slightest traces of ownership of any phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: But somebody who has not done that and tries to perceive giving it all up, it equals death, basically, from their point of view, equals what death is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's that difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like in Buddhism you find another thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nibbāna is just on the level of these other perceptions of light and higher self and cosmos or whatever you might find your shelter in.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like nothing is worth clinging to.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whatever experience you have, fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's perilous.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to understand the extent of gratification, the danger and the escape in order to truly experience what the Buddha was teaching.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not a replacement.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a complete abandonment.